<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Sad and lamentable condition of the Protestants in Ireland being an account of the barbarous proceedings of the natives against the English : as also of the facility of rescuing those distressed Protestants out of the hands of the bloody papists, provided there be a speedy supply from England.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59055</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12318640</idno>
  <idno type="VID">59423</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240970984</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing S240</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32070</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12318640</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59055)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59423)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1026:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Sad and lamentable condition of the Protestants in Ireland being an account of the barbarous proceedings of the natives against the English : as also of the facility of rescuing those distressed Protestants out of the hands of the bloody papists, provided there be a speedy supply from England.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by Randal Taylor ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Protestants --  Ireland.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59423:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59423:1"/>
            <p>THE Sad and Lamentable Condition OF THE PROTESTANTS IN IRELAND.</p>
            <p>BEING An Account of the Barbarous Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the <hi>Natives</hi> against the <hi>ENGLISH.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AS ALSO Of the <hi>Facility</hi> of rescuing those <hi>Distressed</hi> PROTESTANTS out of the Hands of the <hi>Bloody</hi> PAPISTS, provided there be a speedy Supply from <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and are to be Sold by <hi>Randal Taylor,</hi> near <hi>Stationers</hi>-Hall, 1689.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:59423:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:59423:2"/>
            <head>THE Sad and lamentable Condition OF THE PROTESTANTS IN IRELAND. With an Account of the Barbarous Proceedings of the Natives against the <hi>ENGLISH,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THAT the Protestants in <hi>Ireland</hi> are under very great and lamentable Calamities, there is nothing more certain, from the daily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated, most sad and miserable Relations of their Condition. It is a sad thing for them that are upon the spot, to see <hi>Tyrconnil</hi> and his Adherents so Triumphantly carrying all things before him, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arming whom he pleases, imprisoning whom he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, and preparing all things among the Protestants for an absolute Irresistance against Extirpation and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59423:3"/>Massacre; which is a sufficient Testimony of the Barbarity and Inhumanity of those Priests and Jesuits, who animate and encourage them to such Acts of Cruelty and Irreligion. But when we consider that <hi>Ireland</hi> has been, as it were, set up for some years against <hi>England,</hi> and what Levies and Reinforcements have been sent for thence, in all probability to assist the bringing of Popery and Slavery into <hi>England,</hi> it is not to be wondred at, that there should be so much Virulency among the <hi>Irish</hi> against the <hi>English.</hi> It is not the first time that the Question has been so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly debated among the <hi>Irish,</hi> What Course should be taken with the <hi>English,</hi> and all others that were found in the whole Kingdom to be Protestants: And by their subsequent Practices it appears, That no less than another general Massacre is intended. For no Man can be ignorant of the Contrivances of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish Clergy in <hi>Ireland,</hi> ever since the Conquest of that Kingdom, to shake off the English Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; nor of the horrid and barbarous Cruelties they have practised thereunto. For their Ignorance produces so blind a Superstition to the Popish Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that they will most willingly venture their Lives, and whatever their many Rebellions have left them, to farther any thing which they are made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, tends to the Honour of Holy Church. On the other side, their Malice to the <hi>English,</hi> who pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sess good part of their Estates, is so great, that they would be content to be in a worse Condition to a Foreigner, so that they might but gratifie their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge so far, as to have the <hi>English</hi> equal Sufferers with them.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:59423:3"/>
            <p> And yet it is as Evident that the <hi>Romish</hi> Clergy of <hi>Ireland,</hi> have had, both publickly and privately, the Enjoyment and exercise of their Religion, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> more freely since the Reign of <hi>CHARLES</hi> the First, than in se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Years before, by the extraordinary Indulgence of the late Governours. They have had their Titu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Primates, Archbishops, Bishops, Vicar General, Provincial Consistories, Deans, Abbots, Priors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who all liv'd Free, though somewhat covertly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, and exercised their Jurisdictions over the People without controul. They had also their Priests, Jesuits and Friars of late years multiplied into swarms, and in great numbers returned out of <hi>Italy, France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> and other Foreign Parts, where the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Natives, devoted that way, were usually sent to receive their Education, much to the Damage and Disadvantage of the Protestants, and no less of the Papists themselves, would they but consider what Miseries they have endured, and may again be precipitated into, by the means of the ignorant Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish Priests, who know no other Religion but the Enjoyment of their Glebes and Monasteries.</p>
            <p>But that which causes the greatest Admiration, is, That the Noblemen, Private Gentlemen, and others, that are Roman Catholicks, and enjoy great part of their Estates, if not all, should be so infatuated and misled by such a parcel of bloody and designing Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, to act contrary, not only to their Allegiance, but their Honour and their Interest to boot; forgetting the Calamities, by their Means and Industry, brought upon the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> to the utter Ruine and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59423:4"/>Destruction of many Thousands of the <hi>English,</hi> but of many of their own Nation and Relations.</p>
            <p>To bring about these barbarous designs, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpate the <hi>English</hi> Nation, the <hi>Irish</hi> had great expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from the <hi>French,</hi> who were to have Landed by Instructions, either in the County of <hi>Kerry</hi> or the Province of <hi>Munster,</hi> and to have had <hi>Limerick,</hi> and all the Forts and Castles of these parts of <hi>Ireland</hi> put into their hands; and now having the same expectations from the <hi>French</hi> to be Headed by the late King, their great Friend and Patron, is that which carries them to those extraordinary heighths of Insolencies wherein they now reign. 'Tis certain, that the disorders, which the bad Counsels given to that Person, brought <hi>England</hi> into that disorder and confusion, which render it uncapable to give that speedy aid which the present condition of <hi>Ireland</hi> requires; but they consider not in the mean time how often the <hi>French</hi> have deceived them, and what little encouragement they have to give their assistance, in a Country where their friends must bring all their subsistance along with them, all their Arms and Ammunition, and without continual sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies, will find but cold comfort in the depopulated Bogs of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But such is the violence of the Popish Priests and Jesuits in <hi>Ireland,</hi> that their fury and blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thirstiness cares not how it precipitates to the worst of Actions. How sad a thing it must be for the Protestants to be such sufferers, and how cruel for the Papists with such unrelenting Hearts to behold their miseries, but more especially to be actors in them? What a sad face of a City must that be, where
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59423:4"/>Guards are set in every street, at every door of the several Houses, and then for the Protestants to be required to bring forth their Arms upon pain of lying at the mercy of the Souldiers, both Lives and Goods? If this be not the fore-runner of a Massa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre, what can be thought other?</p>
            <p>To justify this, <hi>Tyrconnil</hi> Declares, That being certainly informed of the P. of <hi>Orange</hi>'s intentions to Invade <hi>Ireland,</hi> and that upon Landing, he will endeavour to possess himself of all the Arms, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition and Horses in the custody of private Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, as well to strengthen his own Party, as to weaken his Masters Interest, he thought fit to seize upon all the Arms and serviceable Horses in the City and Suburbs of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and commanded all the Inhabitants to repair with all their Arms, of what nature soever, to the Parish Churches, and there deliver them to appointed Receivers: Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring farther withal, That if any such Arms should be found, upon search, in the Houses of any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants, after the publishing of his Orders, the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons where such Arms should be found, must run the risque of the ill consequences, by disorders from the Souldiers.</p>
            <p>And thus the game, under specious pretences, is about to begin; for, it is but conveighing a Pistol or a Baggonet into the House of any eminent Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant; which so soon as it shall be found, upon a pretended search, then the Souldiers and the Rabble shall be all let loose together to cut the Protestants Throats.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:59423:5"/>
            <p> Other Ravages of the same nature are daily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the Country, and managed with more se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity, and they that make opposition are plundered of all. Even they who had the Lord Deputy's Protection and Licence to keep Arms to defend their Houses, were besieg'd and more hardly used on that very score; in so much, that Sir <hi>Arthur Long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> Mr. <hi>Barton</hi> of <hi>Carrickna-Cross,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Price,</hi> lost all their Goods, and some of them were made Prisoners. Sir <hi>Thomas Newcomen</hi> too is said to be in the same Condition; it being certainly reported, That though he had a Protection and Licence for Arms for Twenty Men, the <hi>Irish</hi> Papists broke into his House, and did not leave the worth of a Groat.</p>
            <p>In a word, the sad and lamentable Condition of the Protestants in <hi>Ireland,</hi> by the Violences of the <hi>Irish,</hi> exceeds all the Relation that can be given of it. For these barbarous Villains not only quarter upon the poor Protestants, but rob and spoil them of their Money, Goods and Cattle. On the 25th. of the last Month, about Midnight, a great number of <hi>Irish</hi> Horse and Foot entred into <hi>Cork;</hi> they dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armed all the Protestants in the Town, and the next day seized all their Horses, and broke into the Houses of several of the principal Citizens, from whence they tookgreat summs of Money, committing the same Villainies in all the Villages of that Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood. Neither fare the Protestants better in <hi>Munster, Lemster</hi> and <hi>Connaught;</hi> for there they have not only disseized them of their Inheritances, but also have plunder'd them of their Arms, Goods and Horses; and not content with depriving them of all their subsistance, have put many of the chiefest of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59423:5"/>them in Prison. In <hi>Dublin</hi> the Protestants are all disarm'd, their Horses taken from them, and many of them plunder'd and cruelly treated by the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, who have also seiz'd on both the Cathedrals and the College; stopping all the Ships, and the poor distressed Passengers that offer to make their escape out of the hands of these bloody Monsters.</p>
            <p>But we need no other instance of the Barbarity and Treachery of the <hi>Irish,</hi> than the ill Treatment of the worthy Captain <hi>Boyle</hi> by Lieutenant-General <hi>Macarty;</hi> who, on the Twenty sixth of the last Month, with a considerable Body of Horse, and two Field Pieces, marched towards <hi>Castlemartir,</hi> the House of the said Captain <hi>Boyle,</hi> who had with him about One hundred and forty Gentlemen and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to defend themselves against the Violences of the <hi>Irish.</hi> But being perswaded to make no Resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, upon the Promise of the Lieutenant General, That neither their Persons or Estates should be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lested; yet notwithstanding this, without having any regard thereto, <hi>Macarty</hi> caused the House to be plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd, and Captain <hi>Boyle,</hi> with many of the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to be carried Prisoners to <hi>Corke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the other side, the Proceedings of <hi>Tyrconnil</hi> cannot choose but flush the new-rais'd Souldiers and all the Popish Party, who finding the Forces and Succors promis'd to the Protestants in <hi>England</hi> so long delay'd, pamper themselves up that a day of Accompt will never come, and therefore speak with contempt of the <hi>Irish</hi> Succours, despise the alteration of Government in <hi>England,</hi> and talk loudly of Invading even <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> it self within a few Months. More than this, they were so bold, as upon a report of the late
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59423:6"/>King's being Landed from <hi>France</hi> at <hi>Kingsale</hi> in <hi>Munster,</hi> the Papists took the Alarm in the North of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and Three Regiments of Horse of <hi>Tyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>connil</hi>'s Crew, quartering in and about <hi>Belturbet,</hi> in the County of <hi>Cavan,</hi> were resolved to execute their fury upon the Protestants thereabouts. To which purpose, Orders were presently given to the said Three Regiments to March, under the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Major <hi>Reily,</hi> a notorious Papist, though a cowardly fellow, toward <hi>Castle-sanderson,</hi> which is about three Miles distance from the said Town; where Captain <hi>Sanderson,</hi> and Captain <hi>Williams,</hi> both good Protestants, and Men of undaunted Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and Resolution, together with most of the Protestants in that County, and as many Forces as they could raise, were retired for safety. Who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Intelligence of the design, drew up their Men upon a Plain before the Castle, and formed them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Troops and Companies, to the number of Four Hundred Horse, and Eight hundred Foot, the most of them pretty well Armed, declaring they would die upon the Place before they would yield to <hi>Tyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>connil</hi>'s Party; and were as good as their Words: For as Major <hi>Reily</hi> appeared with his Horse the next day in the Afternoon, the Protestants boldly advanced toward him and his Party, gave them an utter De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat, took himself and Four of his Captains Prisoners, <hi>viz.</hi> Captain <hi>Gutre,</hi> Captain <hi>Mac-mahon,</hi> Captain <hi>Reily,</hi> and Captain <hi>Foy;</hi> the rest fled, leaving most of their Arms and Horses behind them; while Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptain <hi>Sanderson</hi> sent Four of his Troops, and posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed himself of <hi>Belturbet,</hi> and all the Provisions which the Papists had left in the Town. By which it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59423:6"/>that while the same Courage remains in the Hearts of the Protestants, and the same Cowardice possesses the Minds of the Papists, by timely Assistance from <hi>England,</hi> it would be no difficult thing to reduce that Kingdom to his Majesty's and the Protestant Interest. Nevertheless the disadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage will be very great to those who are under the full Force and Power of these blood-thirsty Rebels.</p>
            <p>This little Prospect therefore between the Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of the Protestants, and the Defect of Valour in the Popish <hi>Irish,</hi> notwithstanding <hi>Tyrconnil</hi>'s Brava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do's upon uncertain Hopes, one would think should draw the <hi>Irish</hi> Papists, were they not infatuated by their Priests and Jesuits, into a consideration, whether they have Force enough and Courage of their own to defend their Country from the Power of the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish,</hi> and those of their own Country, when Asso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciated together. For if they have not, it would be certainly their most prudent way to lay down their Arms in Season, and submit to that Government, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which they have always liv'd in Peace and Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, but when they themselves disturb'd and provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked it. When they had butcher'd several hundreds of peaceable Protestants living among them, though they had the Pope's Blessing and his Bulls of Pardon, and his <hi>Nuncio</hi> to Head them, and Promises from <hi>Spain</hi> to Assist them; and though they started their Rebellion at a time when <hi>Scotland,</hi> and, presently after, <hi>England,</hi> by the Arts of the same jesuitical Incendiaries, that blew them into a Flame, were ingaged in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Combustion, and consequently in the Eye of Reason were unable to yield any Assistance towards the crushing their Hellish Designs: they cannot
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59423:7"/>forget that Providence was pleased to defeat their Projects, to blast their Enterprises, and give them up to so total a Conquest, that at last they became the Scorn of all the World, and there wanted but little to render them as odious and contemptible, and as <hi>Jews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for Foreign Aid, the <hi>Irish</hi> would do well to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider, how little there is to be expected from <hi>France,</hi> that has its hands full already, and is every day in Expectance of more work, and when they have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged themselves beyond going back, they must ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to depend upon the Charity and Discretion of their Assistants whether they will Aid them or no; at least their Supplies will be but faint and small. Where-ever the King of <hi>France</hi> Assists he loves always and designs no other than to get good Footing for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self; and then as the Duke of <hi>Medina Celi</hi> said, They will find his Sword will know no difference between a Catholick and a Heretick, but that he comes to make way for himself; and that though they themselves are Catholicks, the <hi>French</hi> will look upon their Estates to be Hereticks. Though on the other side, suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing that the King of <hi>France</hi> in pure Charity and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miseration of their Condition, should put an Army into his Fleet, with an intention to Land in <hi>Ireland,</hi> unless he were Prince of the Air, and could command the Sea and Tempests, he is not sure to Land them. So that since there is no Confidence to be put in the Power of any Foreign Prince, as it would be their Duty, so it would be their Wisdom to rely upon the Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of their now Natural Prince, whose Mercy and Indulgence is so well known.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:59423:7"/>
            <p> But however, if they will continue in their wicked and horrid Practices, there is no question to be made but the same care and means will be used by Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity which has been formerly observed, as well to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover so large a Portion of the English Dominions, to punish the Obstinacy of the Rebels, and to secure it against all Foreign Power whatsoever, by cutting off their Correspondence with any Foreign Prince or State; by keeping up convenient Garrisons; by the Execution of wholesom Laws to alter their mischie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Constitutions; by a Ministry well settled to Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilize and Instruct them; and by taking strict care to punish all Priests and Jesuits, that are the Nurses of Rebellion, Disturbers of State, mortal Enemies to all Protestant Government, and more especially the common Incendiaries of the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis very true, that it is a <hi>French</hi> Maxim, That a Man ought not to be a Slave to his Word; that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest is Right, and all things lawful that make for Princes Glory and Grandeur. Suppose therefore he should permit some of his Forces to go over into <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as he did to the Succour of <hi>Portugal</hi> against the <hi>Pyrenean</hi> Treaty, and that the <hi>Irish</hi> Papists should join with them, it will most assuredly, as far as the Prospect of humane Judgment will reach, prove their Confusion and Ruine. Considering how early an Army may be transmitted out of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> into <hi>Ireland,</hi> and what an obstinate Defence the Protestants, who are already there embodied will make, before they will depart from their Estates, which they now enjoy, and which they have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:59423:8"/>with so much Expence of Blood. The <hi>French</hi> have Reason to understand and remember the <hi>English</hi> Gallantry. Or, if they have forgot, let them but call to mind <hi>Poictiers, Agin-Court,</hi> or <hi>Crecy,</hi> and they will inform them. But in Case the <hi>French</hi> King should own the Action, and vigorously appear in their Defence; without Question there are some so highly concern'd in point of Interest, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering the present Alliances of <hi>England,</hi> and the Situation of that Kingdom, that he will draw upon him the greatest Naval Power of <hi>Europe;</hi> and of what pernicious Consequence that may be to his Glory, is suitable to his Judgment to consider: Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he could Post his Naval as he used to do his Land-Forces, that they could not be Attacked; and yet that Imagination was confuted at the Relief of <hi>Mons.</hi> Moreover, in Case the <hi>French</hi> King should Transport an Army into <hi>Ireland,</hi> the Conquest of it would not prove to be in an Instant, but a Work of Time; and the more Forces were sent thither, the <hi>Irish,</hi> for want of Provision would be the sooner un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, in regard that a Famine has always put a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod to all Invasions and Rebellions in that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; nor can it be rationally conceived that the <hi>French</hi> can be able to relieve them by Sea, when they are like to have so great a Power against them. For that if the <hi>French</hi> King keep the Sea, they will certainly be fought with; and then let them consider the Consequence. Or if they keep within <hi>Brest,</hi> which is the only Port of <hi>France,</hi> from whence the <hi>Irish</hi> can expect Relief, they have no small Reason to expect to be block'd up, and that their Ships may be Fired in the Port. And indeed the Glory of that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59423:8"/>Action of <hi>Blake,</hi> at the <hi>Canaries,</hi> is worthy of their great Consideration, who entred their Port, and Fired all their Ships in Harbour, notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there were Thirteen Block-Houses, Castles and Works, where an innumerable multitude of Cannon were planted, and Fired most furiously upon the <hi>English</hi> Ships. For where there is a good Wind and Tide, and noble Resolutions, as they need not Question but to find among the <hi>Irish,</hi> there is but little occasion to fear any Artillery whatever. And more than all this, let the <hi>Irish</hi> call to mind the Success which they had, when they were encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged by the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> and assisted by the Pope to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel; the <hi>Spaniard</hi> being then the most Potent Prince in <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that it is not rational for the <hi>Irish</hi> to think, that <hi>France</hi> will ever give them any rational As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistance, but may engage them in a Rebellion, and then leave them to shift for themselves; and so their Rebellion will be no more than a means to bring Ruine and Extirpation upon themselves and their Posterity. The <hi>Irish</hi> would do well to consider the late, but never to be forgotten Case, of the <hi>Mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sineses,</hi> who fled to the Protection of the <hi>French;</hi> who after they had by their Taxes and Oppressions drained away all their Money, deserted them, and left them exposed to the displeasure of the enraged <hi>Spaniard,</hi> and to all the Miseries and Calamities that Revenge could bring upon them. The <hi>Irish</hi> would do well to let this Example be an Answer to all the <hi>French</hi> Charms their Priests shall lay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:59423:9"/>them; and to make them take time to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider, that if they will be so imprudent, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperately Wicked, as to cast off their Obedience to a Good, a Just and Gracious Prince, whether the same Fate and Calamities may not attend them as have done the <hi>Messineses.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true, there was a Horrid Massacre of the <hi>English,</hi> committed by the <hi>Irish,</hi> after they had liv'd together for Forty Years in the greatest Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Happiness imaginable. Yet afterwards, notwithstanding such a Massacre, they were so broken by the <hi>English,</hi> that there was scarce an <hi>Irish</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in <hi>Ireland</hi> that durst hold up his hand against them, and the Kingdom became so depopulated, that considering the vast number of People that were destroyed by those Three great Judgments of Heaven, the Sword, Famine and Plague, there did not remain alive above the eighth part of the <hi>English</hi> Nation, the whole Country being wasted and consumed. So that for sometimes Ten, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Twenty Miles together, all the Kingdom o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, a Traveller should not behold either Man, Bird or Beast; the very Fowls of the Air and wild Beasts of the Field being either Dead, or having forsaken those unfortunate Desolations. While Thousands of the <hi>Irish</hi> lay daily starving for want of Food, but what in their Extremity they got by feeding on the Souldiers Horses, for which they paid many times with the loss of their Lives. Nay, the Famine at last grew to that height, that they not only fed upon Horses, but upon dead Bodies. digg'd up again out of their Graves. A sad Tragedy, which it is heartily wish'd may never be acted over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:59423:9"/>more especially since his Majesty has with so much Grace and Compassion to the <hi>Irish</hi> Nation, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed in several of his Declarations, his Royal Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to restore them to all Enjoyments, which good and dutiful Subjects can expect under so good and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful a Prince. Therefore, at such a Juncture as this, to embrue their Hands in the Blood of their Fellow Subjects, and rebel against a Prince so clement and so faithful to his Promises, and so bring upon themselves the same Calamities or worse, if possible, by betraying the Kingdom into the Hands of a foreign Power, are Acts so full of Horror and Amazement, that no Men, one would think, could be so ungratefully wicked.</p>
            <p>Now that the Lord <hi>Tyrconnil</hi> may be enabled to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware by other mens Harms, we shall give him these following Hints.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Con Oneale,</hi> sirnamed <hi>Bacco,</hi> or the <hi>Lame,</hi> was such an enemy to the <hi>English,</hi> that he left a solemn Curse upon his Posterity, if ever they sow'd Wheat, spake <hi>English,</hi> or built Houses: To him succeeded <hi>Shane Oneale,</hi> who not content with the title of Earl of <hi>Tyrone,</hi> conferr'd upon his Father by <hi>Henry</hi> VIII. would make himself greater by a barbarous kind of Election, throwing up his Shooe over his Head, and taking upon him the Title of <hi>Oneale,</hi> took up Arms against Queen <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> but finding himself too weak, he went into <hi>England,</hi> attended by his Guard of Gallowglasses, bare-headed, curl'd long hair, yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Frocks dy'd with Saffron or Urine, long Sleeves, short Coats, and shaggy Mantles. And thus attended, he fell down at the Queen's feet, confess'd his Crime and Rebellion, with howling, and so obtain'd his Pardon.</p>
            <p>However, he continued not long in his obedience, but ingratefully scorning the Title of Earl of <hi>Tyrone,</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:59423:10"/>Baron of <hi>Duncannon,</hi> conferr'd upon him by the Queen, he would again of his own head assume the great Name of <hi>Oneale,</hi> vaunt himself K. of <hi>Ʋlster,</hi> Leavy Forces, and offer the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland</hi> to <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of <hi>Scots;</hi> and so hated the <hi>English,</hi> that he built a Castle upon the <hi>Lake Eaugh,</hi> which he called <hi>Foughne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal,</hi> or <hi>hatred to the English.</hi> Nay, he hang'd some of his own Men because they eat <hi>English</hi> Bread. Thus he created some troubles; but at last, in his Cups, was stabb'd by those he most confided in.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fitz-Morrice</hi> was so hunted from place to place, by the valour and industry of Sir <hi>John Perrott,</hi> Lord President of <hi>Munster;</hi> that being at last forc'd to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit himself to the Queen's Mercy, he found out the President then at Church at <hi>Killmalock,</hi> and with a hideous howling and crying, besought his Pardon. <hi>Perrott</hi> caus'd the Rebel to take the point of his naked Sword in his hand, and set it to his own Brest, in token that he had receiv'd his Life at the Queen's hands.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Stukely,</hi> who told Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> that he would rather be Sovereign of a Mole-hill, than the highest Subject to the greatest Monarch in Christendom, Shipp'd himself for <hi>Italy,</hi> where according to his nature, boasting of his own worth and actions, he carried himself so cunningly, that at last by his own commendations and flatteries, he wrought himself into the esteem and favour of <hi>Pius</hi> the V. whom he perswaded, that with 3000 Men he would drive the <hi>English</hi> out of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and fire all their Fleet.</p>
            <p>But this Pope dying, <hi>Gregory</hi> the XIII. succeeded him, who being carried on with the same desires, bare the same favour to poor <hi>Stukely,</hi> hoping to get the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland</hi> for his own Son, <hi>John Buon Campagno,</hi> whom he had made Marquess of <hi>Vineola;</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:59423:10"/>and of this Royalty, <hi>Stukely</hi> assur'd him to that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, that the proud Bastard began to think of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Crowns and Scepters. And thus the Pope and his Son were full of hopes of a new Kingdom; and the better to countenance that boasting Factor, as if all <hi>Ireland</hi> were his own, honours him with the Titles of <hi>Baron of Ross, Viscount Morough,</hi> Earl of <hi>Wexford</hi> and <hi>Caterlogh,</hi> and Marquis of <hi>Lemster.</hi> And thus with a Muster of Titles, and a Band of Eight hundred <hi>Italian</hi> Foot, with a Plenary Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence for <hi>Stukely</hi>'s Soul to avoid Purgatory, the <hi>Irish</hi> Champion, with his Titles and Followers, arrives at the Mouth of the River <hi>Teio</hi> in <hi>Portugal;</hi> at what time King <hi>Sebastian</hi> was setting forward for <hi>Africa. Sebastian</hi> hearing of his Arrival, would needs go to see him, and perswade him to venture his Fortune with him, in his <hi>Mauritanian</hi> Expedition. And <hi>Stukely</hi>'s vain Glory was such, that forgetting his <hi>Irish</hi> Affairs, he suffered himself to be over-ruled by the young Prince, and was slain with him in the same Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; and so <hi>Buon Compagno</hi> lost his Kingdom, and he all his Titles.</p>
            <p>And now, <hi>James Fitz-Morrice,</hi> that had been so lately re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into the Queen's Favour, steals into <hi>France,</hi> and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dressing himself to <hi>Henry</hi> III. offers him the Kingdom of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> only desires a small Force to beat out the <hi>English,</hi> and subdue the Nation to the <hi>French</hi> Obedience. But <hi>Henry,</hi> streightned between the <hi>Guisians</hi> and the <hi>Hugonetts,</hi> rejects his Proposition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philip</hi> the Second of <hi>Spain</hi> lends him a more gracious Ear, sends him to <hi>Gregory</hi> XIII. and joins with one <hi>Saunders,</hi> and <hi>Allan</hi> an <hi>Irish</hi> Man, both Doctors and Priests. The first was by the Pope declared his <hi>Nuncio</hi> for <hi>Ireland,</hi> and Blessed with a consecrated Banner, to be known by its <hi>Cross-Keys.</hi> Thus Sanctified with an Infallible Authority, and a little Money in their Fists, with Letters of Recommendation to the <hi>Spanish</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:59423:11"/>King; they hasten into <hi>Spain,</hi> thence Ship for <hi>Ireland,</hi> and Land in <hi>Kerry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Irish</hi> informed of the coming of their <hi>Spanish</hi> and Papal Friends, rise up in Rebellion, in which <hi>Desmond</hi> was not the least; who for the greater advantage of the Cause, murthered <hi>Henry Davils,</hi> an old <hi>English</hi> Gentleman, and a brave old Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, his intimate Acquaintance, whom he used to call Father; together with his Servants; all whom he butcher'd in their Beds, when they least dreamt of any such Treachery. Which <hi>Saunders</hi> commended as a sweet Sacrifice in the sight of God.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Fitz-Morrice,</hi> he thinking to raise the Rebels in other places to his Assistance, took a particular Road; but his Horses tiring upon the way, he plundered fresh Horses from one <hi>William Burgh</hi>'s Plough. Whereupon <hi>Burgh</hi>'s Sons follow him to rescue their Father's Goods, Charge <hi>Fitz-Morrice</hi> and kill him. <hi>Fitz-Morrice</hi> thus slain, <hi>Desmond</hi> takes his Place, fights the <hi>English,</hi> but is routed, and <hi>Allan</hi> the Priest, who had as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured them of Victory by virtue of the Pope's hallowed Banner, is slain.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Italians</hi> and <hi>Spaniards</hi> who had Landed in <hi>Kerry,</hi> began to Fortifie themselves in a Place which they call'd the <hi>Fortress of Gold.</hi> Against them March the Lord <hi>Grey</hi> Lord Deputy, and the Earl of <hi>Ormond;</hi> and by a Trumpet sent to demand of them who they were, and what their Business was there? They answered, That they were sent from the Pope and the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> to whom the Pope had given <hi>Ireland;</hi> for that <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi> had justly forfeited her Title to the Kingdom, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they would keep what they had got, and get more if they could. But their Courage was soon cool'd, for they were forc'd to yield upon Mercy; the Captains being only sav'd, the rest put to the Sword.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Saunders,</hi> he seeing that neither the Pope's Blessing, nor his consecrated Banner, no his legantine Power, nor his foreign Associates, nor native Rebels could prevail against the Fortune of the <hi>English,</hi> rambled up and down among the Woods and Mountains for his own Security, and died miserable. And such we hope will be the ill Success of all those that resist the lawful Sovereignty of King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:59423:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>